Let's look at the solution to our
two-way set associative cache quiz. As
before, the answer to this type of
question requires us to figure out which
bits in the address determine what in
the cache. So the address will be broken
into offset in this case five bits,
index, in this case two bits to tell us
which set we have and the tag. Seven
bits are used by the index and the
offset which means the index will be
determined only by the least significant
two digits. So now we can just figure
out that 0000 3 is like this. Five bits
are the offset. The next two bits are
the index. So this maps to set zero and
we will put F3
there. Next one is F503.
It maps to the same set but this set now
has two places. So we can actually put
F503
in the other line in that set. Next we
have F563
like this. This maps to set number
three. And finally EF63
is going to map to the same set and
we'll put it here. So, as you can see,
with a two-way set associative cache, we
can put more than one block that maps to
the same place in the cache and not have
conflicts. This is why we want to have a
two-way cache or more because it reduces
the number of conflicts. However, it
complicates the tag checks because now
when we're looking for something, we
have two places to search before we are
sure whether it's there or not.